A Finding Aid to the Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner Papers, circa 1914-1984, bulk 1942-1984, in the Archives of American Art AAA.polljack
Archives of American Art
Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner papers
bulk 1942-1984
circa 1914-1984
AAA.polljack
Archives of American Art
15.6 Linear feet
The papers of abstract expressionist painters Jackson Pollock and wife Lee Krasner measure 15.6 linear feet and date from circa 1914 to 1984, with the bulk of the material dating from 1942 to 1984. The collection documents their personal and professional lives, as well as the legacy of Jackson Pollock's work after his death. Found are biographical material, correspondence, writings by Krasner and others, research material, business and financial records, printed material, scrapbooks, artwork by others, photographs, interview transcripts, audio and video recordings, and motion picture film.
Pollock, Jackson
Provenance
The papers of Jackson Pollock were donated in 1983 by Lee Krasner through Eugene V. Thaw shortly before her death. Additional material about Pollock and the papers of Lee Krasner were donated in 1985 by Eugene V. Thaw, executor of Lee Krasner's estate.
Related Material
Found in the Archives of American Art are the Charles Pollock Papers, 1902-1990, which includes correspondence, photographs, and other files relating to his brother, Jackson Pollock. Other resources in the Archives are oral history interviews with Lee Krasner, including a series of interviews conducted by Dorothy Seckler between 1964 and 1968, and interviews conducted by Barbara Rose in 1966 and Doloris Holmes in 1972.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2006 and 2008. The Jackson Pollock papers and photographs from the Lee Krasner papers were scanned from originals. The bulk of the Lee Krasner papers were digitized from 7 reels of microfilm. In total, there are 15096 images available. All of the sound recordings have also been digitized and are available at the Archives of American Art offices.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.
Biographical Note
Jackson Pollock was born in 1912, in Cody, Wyoming, the youngest of five sons. His family moved several times during his childhood, finally settling in Los Angeles. In 1930 he joined his older brother, Charles, in New York City, and studied with Regionalist painter Thomas Hart Benton at the Art Students League of New York. Pollock worked during the 1930s for the Works Progress Administration's Federal Art Project. During 1936 he worked in artist David Alfaro Siqueiros's Experimental Workshop. In 1938 he began psychiatric treatment for alcoholism, and his artwork was greatly influenced by Jungian analysis and the exploration of unconscious symbolism.
In 1943 Pollock had his first one-man exhibition at Peggy Guggenheim's New York gallery, Art of this Century, and continued to exhibit there over the next several years. A major turning point in Pollock's life and art was in 1945 when he married fellow artist Lee Krasner and moved to East Hampton, Long Island. There he developed his mature painting style, and became famous for his abstract pouring technique on large canvases. The height of his creativity spanned from 1947 to 1952, and his work was promoted by art critic Clement Greenberg. Along with other abstract expressionists including Hans Hofmann, Alfonso Ossorio, and Barnett Newman, he joined the Betty Parsons Gallery in 1947. He had his most successful one-man show in 1950 which was widely publicized and praised. This exhibition, combined with a 1949 feature article in LIFE magazine, made Pollock an American celebrity.
In 1952 Pollock moved his work to Sidney Janis Gallery and returned to earlier motifs in a search for new breakthroughs. The last few years of his life he suffered from mental and physical health problems, and in August, 1956 he died in a car accident. His wife, Lee Krasner, oversaw his estate and worked with many museums, including the Museum of Modern Art, on Pollock retrospective exhibitions.
Lee Krasner was born Lenore Krassner in 1908 in Brooklyn, New York to Russian immigrant parents. In 1926 she was admitted to the Women's Art School of The Cooper Union, and in 1928 she attended the Art Students League. After graduating from The Cooper Union in 1929, she attended the National Academy of Design until 1932. After briefly attending City College and Greenwich House, she worked for the Public Works of Art Project and the Temporary Emergency Relief Administration, and finally became an assistant in 1935 on the WPA Federal Art Project, Mural Division. From 1937 to 1940 she studied at the Hans Hofmann School of Fine Arts and began exhibiting with the American Abstract Artists group.
In 1942 Krasner met Pollock as they were both preparing to exhibit work in the same show. Although they married and she became immersed in his career, she continued to exhibit her own work with other abstract artists and from 1946 to 1949 worked on the Little Image painting series. In 1953 she began working on collages, a medium she would come back to again later in her career. After Pollock's death her work was greatly influence by her sadness and anger, creating a visible evolution of her style.
For the rest of her career, Krasner consistently exhibited her work in both group and solo exhibitions. She had her first retrospective at Whitechapel Gallery, London, in 1965, and in 1966, she joined Marlborough Gallery, New York which represented Pollock's work as well. In the 1970s and early 1980s Krasner won many awards for her achievement in the visual arts, including the Augustus St. Gaudens Medal and the Chevalier de l'Ordre des Arts et des Lettres. She returned to the medium of collage, and in 1976 joined the Pace Gallery, New York. In 1981 she joined the Robert Miller Gallery, New York. Lee Krasner continued creating art until her death in 1984.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of abstract expressionist painters Jackson Pollock and wife Lee Krasner measure 15.6 linear feet and date from circa 1914 to 1984, with the bulk of the material dating from 1942 to 1984. The collection documents their personal and professional lives, as well as the legacy of Jackson Pollock's work after his death. Found are biographical material, correspondence, writings by Krasner and others, research material, business and financial records, printed material, scrapbooks, artwork by others, photographs, interview transcripts, audio and video recordings, and motion picture film.
The collection is divided into two series, the first of which focuses on Pollock and includes his scattered papers dating from circa 1914 to his death in 1956, as well as Krasner's papers dating from his death to 1984 about managing Pollock's legacy. This series includes biographical materials, including transcripts and audio recordings of an interview with William Wright in 1949; Pollock's and Krasner's correspondence with Thomas Hart Benton, Betty Parsons Gallery, Bill Davis, B. H. Friedman, Reginald Isaacs, Sidney Janis, Violet De Lazlo, Martha Jackson Gallery, Alfonso Ossorio, Tony Smith, and Clyfford Still, and with one another; Krasner's correspondence concerning Pollock's estate and artwork after his death; numerous writings about Pollock, including an original draft of Bryan Robertson's biography and an essay by Clement Greenberg.
James Valliere extensive research files on Pollock for a never-published biography were given to Krasner and filed in Series 1. These include scattered correspondence with Lee Krasner, and Pollock's family and friends, including Charles Pollock, Thomas Hart Benton, and Robert Motherwell. There are also transcripts of interviews Valliere conducted with Pollock's friends and colleagues, including James Brooks, Dorothy Dehner, Clement Greenberg, Reuben Kadish, Lee Krasner, Charles Maddox, Mrs. Sanford McCoy, Daniel T. Miller, Robert Miller, and Tony Smith. The original audio reels and duplicates exist for many and are filed here. Additional interviews were conducted with Willem de Kooning, Alfonso Ossorio, and Burton Rouche, but not transcribed - these are filed in Series 1.10, Audio Recordings and Motion Picture Film.
Also found in Series 1 are scattered business records documenting Krasner's handling of Pollock's estate and legacy; printed materials relating to Pollock, including published biographies, exhibition catalogs, and clippings; two scrapbooks; and a sketchbook by an unidentified artist. Numerous photographs of Pollock include childhood and family photographs, photographs of Pollock in his studio by Hans Namuth, Rudy Burckhardt, and Wilfrid Zogbaum, photographs of Pollock with Lee Krasner, and exhibition photographs. Audio recordings and motion film in Series 1 include a 1964 16mm film about Pollock (VHS copies are available) and reel-to-reel recordings of untranscribed interviews of Pollock's friends and colleagues by James Valliere, including interviews with Willem de Kooning and Alfonso Ossorio. Additional transcribed interviews are filed in subseries 1.4.
Lee Krasner's papers documenting her own career are arranged in Series 2 and date from 1927-1984. Biographical materials include resumes and awards, school documents, family documentation, and exhibition lists. Her correspondence with artist friends and art colleagues is extensive and includes many letters from artists such as Philip Johnson, Ray Eames, Cleve Gray, and Hans Namuth. She also maintained correspondence with many art historians and critics, curators, gallery owners, collectors, arts-related and social organizations, admirers, and family members.
There are thirteen transcripts of interviews with Krasner by Bruce Glaser, Barbara Cavaliere, Andrew Forge, Emily Wasserman, Barbara Rose, and others. The original audio recordings for these transcripts are filed in series 2.10, along with other audio recordings for which there are no transcripts, including interviews by John Gruen, Delores Holmes, Mercedes Matter, the Martha Dean Radio Show, NBC Today Show, and WQXR radio. There are also audio recordings of Krasner's lectures in series 2.10.
Krasner's papers also include writings and reminiscences by Krasner; writings about Krasner; printed materials such as exhibition catalogs and clippings; and one scrapbook containing clippings and photographs. Numerous photographs are of Krasner, including portrait photographs taken by Hans Namuth; of Krasner with Jackson Pollock and family and friends, and of her exhibitions and artwork.
Users should note that Pollock's and Krasner's papers contain similar types of material that often overlap in subject matter, especially among the correspondence and photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series 1: Jackson Pollock papers and Lee Krasner papers about Jackson Pollock, circa 1914-1984 (Box 1-7, 16, OV 18; 7.0 linear feet)
Series 2: Lee Krasner papers, circa 1927-1984 (Box 7-15, 17; 8.6 linear feet)
Benton, Thomas Hart, 1889-1975; Betty Parsons Gallery; Brooks, James, 1906-; Burkhardt, Rudy; Cavaliere, Barbara; Davis, Bill; De Kooning, Willem, 1904-; Dehner, Dorothy, 1901-1994; Eames, Ray; Forge, Andrew; Friedman, B. H. (Bernard Harper), 1926-; Glaser, Jane R.; Gray, Cleve; Greenberg, Clement, 1909-; Gruen, John; Holmes, Doloris; Isaacs, Reginald R., 1911-; Janis, Sidney, 1896-; Johnson, Philip, 1906-; Kadish, Reuben, 1913-; Krasner, Lee, 1908-, Photographs; Krasner, Lee, 1908-; Maddox, Charles; Martha Jackson Gallery; Matter, Mercedes; McCoy, Sanford, Mrs.; Miller, Daniel; Miller, Robert, 1932 Apr. 17-; Motherwell, Robert; Namuth, Hans; Ossorio, Alfonso, 1916-; Pollock, Charles C.; Pollock, Jackson, 1912-1956, Photographs; Rose, Barbara; Rouche, Burton; Smith, Tony, 1912-; Still, Clyfford, 1904-; Valliere, James; Wasserman, Tamara E.; Wright, William; Zogbaum, Wilfrid, 1915-1965; Abstract expressionism; Art -- Economic aspects; Interviews; Motion pictures (visual works); Painters -- New York (State); Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sound recordings; Transcripts; Video recordings
- Jackson Pollock papers and Lee Krasner papers about Jackson Pollock, circa 1914-1984; Series 1; (Box 1-7, 16, OV 18; 7.0 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains Jackson Pollock's papers and Lee Krasner's papers about managing Jackson Pollock's artistic legacy. Biographical material includes artist statements and notes, a transcript of an interview with William Wright and the original audio recording, Pollock's birth certificate, and his passport. Correspondence, both personal and professional and spanning 55 years, includes Pollock's and Krasner's correspondence with museums, gallery owners, biographers, students, fans, family, and fellow artists. Correspondents include, among others, Pollock's teacher Thomas Hart Benton and friends Reginald Isaacs, Clyfford Still, Alfonso Ossorio, and Tony Smith. Writings about Pollock include drafts of essays, articles, lectures, and biographies and include essays by Lee Krasner and Clement Greenberg.
  James Valliere extensive research files on Pollock for a never-published biography were given to Krasner. The files include scattered research notes, an inventory of Pollock's library, correspondence with Lee Krasner, and Pollock's family and friends, including Charles Pollock, Thomas Hart Benton, and Robert Motherwell. There are also transcripts of interviews Valliere conducted with Pollock's friends and colleagues, including James Brooks, Dorothy Dehner, Clement Greenberg, Reuben Kadish, Lee Krasner, Charles Maddox, Mrs. Sanford McCoy, Daniel T. Miller, Robert Miller, and Tony Smith. The original audio reels and duplicate tapes for many of the transcripts are filed here. There are photographs of two of the interview sessions. Audio recordings for which there are no transcripts are filed in series 1.10 Audio and Video Recordings and Film.
  Business records primarily concern Lee Krasner's handling of the exhibition and sale of Pollock's artwork after his death. Included are a guest book for the Venice "Bienale", exhibition lists, account statements and inventory lists, lists of owners of his work, appraisal documents, legal documents, receipts, and other miscellaneous records. Printed material consists of book proofs, numerous newspaper and magazine clippings spanning forty years, and as well as exhibition catalogs, announcements, and invitations to solo and group exhibitions. This series also includes two scrapbooks kept by Pollock and Krasner of news clippings and exhibition announcements, and one sketchbook by an unidentified artist.
  Numerous rare photographs found in this series include those of Pollock as a child, with his family and friends, with Lee Krasner, and at work in his Long Island studio, some of which were taken by photographers Hans Namuth and Rudy Burckhardt. Also found are photographs of exhibitions of Pollock's artwork. Audio and video recordings and film in this series include the motion picture film "Jackson Pollock: A Reconsideration," VHS copies of same, and several untranscribed reel-to-reel audio recordings of interviews about Pollock with Alfonso Ossorio, Willem De Kooning, Ruth and Tino Nivola, and Burton Rouche conducted by James Valliere during his research. Audio recordings of interviews with transcripts are filed with Valliere's research files in 1.4.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This series has been scanned in its entirety, except for photographs of works of art, copy prints and negatives, motion picture film, published books, and a few folders of newsclippings. All of the sound recordings in this series have also been digitized for research access.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged into 10 subseries:
  1.1: Biographical Material, circa 1938-1956
  1.2: Correspondence, circa 1929-1984
  1.3: Writings by Others, 1950-circa 1983
  1.4: James Valliere Research Material on Jackson Pollock, 1963-1972
  1.5: Business Records, circa 1942-1983
  1.6: Printed Material, 1942-1983
  1.7: Scrapbooks, 1943-1957
  1.8: Artwork by Others, undated
  1.9: Photographs, circa 1914-1969
  1.10: Audio and Video Recordings and Film, 1964, 1966
  - Biographical Material, circa 1938-1956; 1.1
    Biographical material includes eleven folders of biographical statements and various notes by Pollock, as well as identification items such as his birth certificate and passport. Also found is a audio recording and transcript of a 1949 interview of Pollock by his neighbor William Wright.
    - Biographical Statements, circa 1947-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Birth Certificate Copy, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notes by Pollock, circa 1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Passport, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Selective Service Form, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Social Security Card, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jackson Pollock Interview by William Wright, 1949; 2 sound tape reels Duplicates; 1 sound tape reels Includes transcript Original; 2 Sound cassettes Duplicates (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
      Sound cassettes are access copies.
  - Correspondence, circa 1929-1984; 1.2
    Correspondence prior to 1956 is Jackson Pollock's, and correspondence after 1956 is Lee Krasner's concerning Pollock's artwork and estate. Correspondence is with galleries and museums that exhibited Pollock's work, including several folders concerning exhibitions at the Museum of Modern Art. There is fan fan mail, student inquiries, requests for reproductions, and correspondence concerning restoration work. Correspondents of note include Thomas Hart Benton, Tony Smith, Reginald Isaacs, Clyfford Still, and Alfonso Ossorio, gallery owners Betty Parsons, Sidney Janis, and Martha Jackson, and biographers B.H. Friedman, Francis O'Connor, and Bryan Robertson. Also found are condolence letters and flower cards to Lee Krasner after Pollock's death. There is also a 1936 letter to Pollock from David Alfaro Siqueiros and postcards from Helen Frankenthaler and Clement Greenberg.
    Files are arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent or subject.
    - Arts Council of Great Britain, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Baltimore Museum of Art, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Benton, Thomas Hart, 1935-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Betty Parsons Gallery, 1949-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Centre George Pompidou, 1977-1984; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Condolence Letters, 1956, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-22)
    - Condolence Flower Cards, 1956; (not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Dallas Museum for Contemporary Arts, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - De Lazlo, Violet, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Davis, Bill, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Dickler, Gerald, 1956-1979; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 27-30)
    - Exhibitions and Artwork Loans, 1950-1984; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
    - Fan Mail to Pollock, 1948-circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Fogg Museum of Art, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Friedman, B. H., 1955-1961, 1968-1980 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Gibbs, David, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Heller, Ben, 1955-1963, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Henderson, Joseph, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Howell, Douglas, 1954-1955, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Institute of Contemporary Art, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Isaacs, Reginald, 1949-1955 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Jackson Pollock Catalogue Raisonne, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Jackson, Martha, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Janis, Sidney, 1943, 1953-1976 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Kluger, Richard (Simon & Schuster), 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Krasner, Lee (Correspondence with Pollock), 1943, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Kulicke Frames, Inc., 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Langhorne, Elizabeth, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Lawsuit filed by Peggy Guggenheim, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Littlefield, William H., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Marlborough Fine Art, Ltd., 1961-1976; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 51-54)
    - McCoy, Jason, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1966, 1980-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Musee d'Art Moderne de la Ville de Paris, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Museum of Modern Art, "Jackson Pollock" Exhibition, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Museum of Modern Art, VI Bienal, Sao Paulo, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Museum of Modern Art, "Jackson Pollock: 1912-1956" International Exhibition, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Museum of Modern Art, "New American Painting,", 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Museum of Modern Art, "Documenta II", 1959 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Museum of Modern Art, "Jackson Pollock: Works on Paper", 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Museum of Modern Art, "Jackson Pollock" Exhibition, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Museum of Modern Art, Miscellaneous, 1949-1983; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Namuth, Hans, 1963-1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - O'Connor, Francis V., 1957, 1964-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ossorio, Alfonso, 1950-1955, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Painting Restoration, 1957-1959, 1966-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Pollock Family, 1929-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Putzel, Howard (Art of this Century), 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Requests for Reproductions and Use of Pollock Images, 1952-1984; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - Robertson, Bryan, 1959-1960, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Rubin, William, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Smith, Tony, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Still, Clyfford, 1952-1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Student Requests for Information, 1951-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Sweeney, James Johnson, 1943-1944, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Thames and Hudson, Ltd., 1959-1964, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Wagstaff, Samuel (Wadsworth Athenaeum), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1954-1955, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - General Correspondence, 1936-1970, undated; (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-26)
    - General Correspondence, 1971-1984, undated; (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 27-32)
  - Writings by Others, 1950-circa 1983, undated; 1.3
    Found here are essays, articles, lectures, and biographies about Jackson Pollock. There is an original draft of the Bryan Robertson biography of Jackson Pollock, an essay by Clement Greenberg, and an essay written by Lee Krasner after Pollock's death which discusses his career, personal life, and their relationship.
    Items are arranged alphabetically by author's last name.
    - Bruno Alfieri, "L'Arte Moderna: A Short Talk on The Pictures of Jackson Pollock,", undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Lance Compa, "Jackson Pollock: Art and Cosmos,", undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Francine du Plessix and Cleve Gray, "Who Was Jackson Pollock,", undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Marilyn G. Foley, "Jackson Pollock: Where the Action Is,", circa 1967 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - B.H. Friedman, "Sketches for a Portrait: Jackson Pollock,", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Robert Goodnough, "Jackson Pollock,", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Clement Greenberg, "Jackson Pollock,", circa 1957 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Stanley Harrison, "Lavender Mist by Jackson Pollock: A Critique,", circa 1966 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Lee Krasner, "Pollock,", undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Rosalind E. Krauss, Untitled Essay, circa 1981 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Krauss/Namuth, Untitled Essay, circa 1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - London Exhibition Catalog, draft copy, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - John Bernard Myers, Review of Jackson Pollock: The Last Sketchbook, circa 1983 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Francis O'Connor, "Hans Namuth's Photographs of Jackson Pollock as Art Historical Documentation", undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Francis O'Connor, "Jackson Pollock and the WPA Federal Art Project: 1935 to 1943,", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 47)